I'm going to tell you about one of the world's largest problems
سأقوم باخباركم حول أحد أكبر المشاكل العالمية
and how it can be solved.
وكيف يمكن حلها.
I'd like to start with a little experiment.
أريد أن أبدأ بتجربة بسيطة.
Could you put your hand up if you wear glasses or contact lenses,
هل يمكنك رفع يدك اذا كنت ترتدي نظارة نظر أو عدسات لاصقة،
or you've had laser refractive surgery?
أو اذا كنت خضعت لعملية تصحيح نظر بالليزر؟
Now, unfortunately, there are too many of you for me to do the statistics properly.
الآن، لسوء الحظ، هناك الكثير منكم بالنسبة لي حتى أقوم بالإحصائيات الصحيحة.
But it looks like -- I'm guessing -- that it'll be about 60 percent of the room
لكن يبدو -- أُخمّن- أنه سيكون حوالي ستون في المائة من القاعة
because that's roughly the fraction of developed world population
لأن ذلك تقريبا هو نسبة جزء من سكان العالم المتقدم
that have some sort of vision correction.
الذين لديهم نوع من تصحيح النظر.
The World Health Organization estimates --
تقديرات منظمة الصحة العالمية--
well, they make various estimates of the number of people who need glasses --
حسناً، يقومون بتقديرات متعددة لعدد الناس الذين يحتاجون لنظارات--
the lowest estimate is 150 million people.
أقلها هو مائة وخمسون مليون شخص.
They also have an estimate of around a billion.
لديهم أيضاً تقدير لحوالي البليون.
But in fact, I would argue that we've just done an experiment here and now,
لكن في الحقيقة، أنا أزعم أننا قمنا بتجربة هنا والآن،
which shows us that the global need for corrective eyewear
التي تظهر لنا أن الاحتياج العالمي للنظارات التصحيحية
is around half of any population.
هو حوالي نصف السكان في أي مكان.
And the problem of poor vision, is actually not just a health problem,
ومشكلة النظر الضعيف، في الواقع ليست فقط مشكلة صحية،
it's also an educational problem,
لكنها أيضاً مشكلة تعليمية،
and it's an economic problem, and it's a quality of life problem.
وهي مشكلة إقتصادية، وهي مشكلة نوعية الحياة.
Glasses are not very expensive. They're quite plentiful.
النظارات ليست غالية جداً. وهي متوفرة جداً.
The problem is, there aren't enough eye care professionals in the world
المشكلة هي، أنه لا يوجد مختصي عيون محترفين في العالم
to use the model of the delivery of corrective eyewear
لاستخدام نموذج إيصال النظارات التصحيحية
that we have in the developed world.
الذي لدينا في العالم المتقدم.
There are just way too few eye care professionals.
يوجد عدد قليل من مختصي العيون المحترفين.
So this little slide here shows you an optometrist
إذاً هذه الشريحة هنا تعرض لنا طبيب عيون
and the little blue person represents about 10,000 people
ويمثل الرجل الأزرق الصغير هنا حوالي عشرة آلالاف شخص
and that's the ratio in the U.K.
وهذه النسبة في المملكة المتحدة.
This is the ratio of optometrists to people in sub-Saharan Africa.
وهذه هي نسبة أخصائيو العيون في أفريقيا جنوب الصحراء.
In fact, there are some countries in sub-Saharan Africa
في الحقيقة، هناك العديد من البلدان في أفريقيا جنوب الصحراء
where there's one optometrist for eight million of the population.
حيث نسبة أخصائي العيون هي واحد الى ثمانية ملايين نسمة.
How do you do this? How do you solve this problem?
كيف يمكن التعامل مع هذا؟ كيف يمكن حل هذه المشكلة؟
I came up with a solution to this problem,
لقد توصلت الى حل لهذه المشكلة،
and I came up with a solution based on adaptive optics for this.
ووصلت لحل يقوم على البصريات التكييفية لهذا الغرض.
And the idea is you make eye glasses, and you adjust them yourself
والفكرة هي أن تصنع نظارات، وتقوم بضبطها بنفسك
and that solves the problem.
وذلك يحل المشكلة.
What I want to do is to show you that one can make a pair of glasses.
ما أريد فعله هو أن أبين لكم أنه يمكن أن تصنع نظارات.
I shall just show you how you make a pair of glasses. I shall pop this in my pocket.
يجب علي فقط أن أعرض لكم كيفية صنع نظارات. يجب أن أضع هذا في جيبي.
I'm short sighted. I look at the signs at the end, I can hardly see them.
أنا قصير النظر. أنظر الى العلامات في النهاية، أستطيع رؤيتها بصعوبة.
So -- okay, I can now see that man running out there,
إذاً-- حسناً، أستطيع رؤية ذلك الرجل يجري هناك،
and I can see that guy running out there.
وأستطيع رؤية ذلك الشخص يجري هناك.
I've now made prescription eyewear to my prescription.
لقد صنعت الآن وصفة لنظارة طبية لنظري.
Next step in my process.
الخطوة التالية في طريقتي.
So, I've now made eye glasses to my prescription.
إذاً، لقد صنعت الآن نظارات نظر تلائم نظري.
Okay, so I've made these glasses and ...
حسناً، لقد صنعت هذه النظارات و...
Okay, I've made the glasses to my prescription and ...
حسناً، لقد صنعت النظارات الملائمة لنظري و...
... I've just ...
...أنا فقط...
And I've now made some glasses. That's it.
لقد صنعت الآن النظارات. ها هي.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Now, these aren't the only pair in the world.
الآن، ليست هذه النظارات الوحيدة في العالم.
In fact, this technology's been evolving.
في الحقيقة، هذه التقنية تتطور.
I started working on it in 1985,
لقد بدأت العمل فيها عام 1985،
and it's been evolving very slowly.
ولقد كانت تتطور ببطء للغاية.
There are about 30,000 in use now.
هناك حوالي ثلاثين ألفاً مستخدمة الآن.
And they're in fifteen countries. They're spread around the world.
وموزعة على خمسة عشرة بلداً. في كل أنحاء العالم.
And I have a vision, which I'll share with you.
ولدي رؤيتي ، التي سأتقاسمها معكم.
I have a global vision for vision.
لدي رؤية عالمية للنظر .
And that vision is to try to get a billion people
وتلك الرؤية هي محاولة جعل بليون شخص
wearing the glasses they need by the year 2020.
يرتدون نظارات يحتاجونها بحلول عام 2020.
To do that -- this is an early example of the technology.
لفعل ذلك-- هذا نموذج مبكر لهذه التكنلوجيا.
The technology is being further developed --
ويجري تطوير هذه التكنلوجيا أكثر--
the cost has to be brought down.
يجب تقليل التكلفة.
This pair, in fact, these currently cost about 19 dollars.
هذه النظارات، في الواقع، تكلف حوالي 19 دولاراً حالياً.
But the cost has to be brought right down.
لكن يجب تقليل التكلفة.
It has to be brought down because we're trying to serve populations
يجب أن تقلل التكلفة لأننا نحاول خدمة الناس
who live on a dollar a day.
الذين يعيشون على دولار يومياً.
How do you solve this problem?
كيف يمكننا حل هذه المشكلة؟
You start to get into detail.
بدأتم في الدخول الى التفاصيل.
And on this slide, I'm basically explaining all the problems you have.
وفي هذه الشريحة، أنا أشرح ببساطة كل المشاكل التي لديكم.
How do you distribute? How do you work out how to fit the thing?
كيف يمكن توزيعها؟ كيف يمكن عملها لتناسب هذا الشئ؟
How do you have people realizing that they have a vision problem?
كيف يمكنك إقناع الناس أن لديهم مشكلة في النظر؟
How do you deal with the industry?
كيف يمكنك التعامل مع القطاع الصناعي؟
And the answer to that is research.
والجواب لذلك هو الأبحاث.
What we've done is to set up the Center for Vision in the Developing World
ما أنجزناه هو مركز للبصريات في العالم النامي
here in the university.
هنا في الجامعة.
If you want to know more, just come have a look at our website. Thank you.
اذا أردتم معرفة المزيد، ألقو نظرة على موقعنا الإلكتروني. شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)